<!-- ====== Getting Started ==================================================== -->
<chapter id="begin">
  <title id="begin-title">Getting Started</title>

  <!-- ====== What is CVS? ===================================================== -->
  <section id="begin.whatcvs">
    <title id="begin.whatcvs-title">What is <acronym>CVS</acronym>?</title>
    <para>
    <acronym>CVS</acronym>, or the Concurrent Versioning System, is a
    version control system. Version control systems are generally used as part
    of the software development cycle to track and co-ordinate source code
    changes among a team of developers. 
    </para>
    <para>
    For example, bugs sometimes creep in when software is modified, and you
    might not detect the bug until a long time after you make the
    modification. With <acronym>CVS</acronym>, you can easily retrieve old
    versions to see exactly which change caused the bug. This can sometimes be a
    big help. 
    </para>
    <para>
    You could of course save every version of every file you have ever
    created. This would however waste an enormous amount of disk
    space. <acronym>CVS</acronym> stores all the  versions of a file in a single
    file in a clever way that only stores the differences between versions. 
    </para>
    <para>
    <acronym>CVS</acronym> also helps you if you are part of a group of people
    working on the same project. It is all too easy to overwrite each others'
    changes unless you are extremely careful. Some editors, like GNU Emacs, try
    to make sure that the same file is never modified by two people at the same
    time. Unfortunately, if someone is using another editor, that safeguard will
    not work. <acronym>CVS</acronym> solves this problem by insulating the
    different developers from each other. Every developer works in his own
    sandbox, and <acronym>CVS</acronym> merges the work when each developer is
    done. 
    </para>
  </section>

  <!-- ====== What is TortoiseCVS? ============================================= -->

  <section id="begin.whattortoisecvs">
    <title id="begin.whattortoisecvs-title">What is TortoiseCVS?</title>
    <para>
      TortoiseCVS is a front-end client to make using <acronym>CVS</acronym>
  easier and more intuitive. It allows developers to work with files
  controlled by <acronym>CVS</acronym> directly from <productname>Windows
  Explorer</productname>. 
    </para>
    <para>
      One of the major drawbacks of <acronym>CVS</acronym> is the command-line
  interface that is provided. Many developers today are becoming more
  accustomed to the graphical integrated development environments
  (<acronym>IDEs</acronym>). TortoiseCVS aims to provide that
  "point-and-click" environment in a clever and intuitive way. 
    </para>
    <para>
    Note that TortoiseCVS is a CVS <emphasis>client</emphasis>, not a
    <emphasis>server</emphasis>. This document assumes that you either know how
    to set up your own server, or that you are using a server that somebody else
    set up. If you want to learn about setting up a CVS server, see <xref linkend="resources.cvsbook"/>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <!-- ====== Where to Begin? =================================================== -->

  <section id="begin.wherebegin">
    <title id="begin.wherebegin-title">Where to Begin?</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The best way to learn how to use TortoiseCVS is to play with
  it. Start by <link linkend="ref.install">installing TortoiseCVS</link>. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you are new to CVS start following along with <link linkend="basic" endterm="basic-title"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Once you've learned the ropes check out the advanced features in
  <link linkend="advanced" endterm="advanced-title"/>. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          For pure reference, the chapters <link linkend="ref"
  endterm="ref-title"/> and <link linkend="dialogs" endterm="dialogs-title"/>
  will help you get the most out of TortoiseCVS. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          And finally check out <link linkend="tips" endterm="tips-title"/> for
  a complete and enjoyable version control experience. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="begin.bugs">
  <title id="begin.bugs-title">Errors and Omissions in this Manual</title>
  <para>
  This manual is not perfect, although we try to make it better all the time.
  If you find something which you believe is wrong, or if you think something is missing from the 
  manual, please
  <ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/?func=add&amp;group_id=48103&amp;atid=451972">let us know</ulink>.
  (Please set the <guilabel>Category</guilabel> to <literal>Documentation</literal>; you do not need to include your OS
  version and CVSROOT).
</para>
  </section>
  
</chapter>
